[SPEAKER_01]: How can taking on the precept of non-entertainment help reveal the subtler and more fundamental tendency towards distraction?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, by taking on the precepts.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how it would reveal it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, how do you... how do you draw that line for yourself when you... you're kind of comfortable within that precept, but the tendency to distraction still exists?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you mean, you're not giving in to the entertainment, in a sense of breaking the precept, but are still distracting yourself?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, contrasting that with things that take up your time and attention, and you might kind of just... because they seem like they would be distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're not so sure where to draw the difference between that intentional distraction and things that just happen to take time but are useful...
[SPEAKER_01]: Things that you have to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's the difference.
[SPEAKER_02]: Did you initiate it or do you just have to do it?
[SPEAKER_02]: And how far?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, when you initiate something, just ask, where is this coming from?
[SPEAKER_02]: How distracting it will be?
[SPEAKER_02]: And what if I...
[SPEAKER_02]: What if I don't do it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Is the mind resisting that idea?
[SPEAKER_02]: Then you know there is some impulse behind me needing to do something.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's not really, I don't know, it's not really a brain science.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you have to say no, see whether the mind resists, sometimes say yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's all within the precepts.
[SPEAKER_02]: See whether the mind becomes completely unaware of itself when you're distracted.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then other things come up, and then recognize, aha, well, last time, when I did what I had to do, next four hours, I was completely distracted, and in the evening, sensuality came, and ill-will came, because the mind was completely switched off.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, next time, when I have to do something, well, I'll be more careful and don't go that far, internally.
[SPEAKER_02]: Keep at least some degree of self-awareness in regard to things, even while I'm doing them.
[SPEAKER_00]: It sounds familiar, like this, you, maybe, some time of the day, you know you're bored, there's suffering there, in the background, and
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, let me just... let me read the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let me go into this.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you start reading the suttas because it's kind of, you know, that's okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: But... and you do that for four hours.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you started because you were bored.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start... so you're just carrying that whole energy with you, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're developing that resistance to boredom by studying the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: by studying the suttas and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, at the end of it, after four hours, you're still as agitated as ever and...
[SPEAKER_02]: I think it's more like the question of duration there, rather than... because, yeah, reading the suttas, even if you do it for the distracting purposes, if you're actually reading them, they are pointing back to things you're trying to distract yourself from.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it can kind of help you.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, yes, if you are doing it for four or five hours, means, okay, you're doing it with, like, a even more diminished self-awareness, and I think that will be the problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, spend four hours whereby you haven't acknowledged the fact that you are distracting yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: As opposed to, you start with a distraction, but out in, you become way too self-aware, because you're actually reading the suttas, and thinking about those things, and the distraction disappeared, the motivation disappeared, to distract yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, again, are you doing the suttas?
[SPEAKER_02]: Are you reading the suttas?
[SPEAKER_02]: Even through the desire of distraction, but are you still actually searching for the meaning?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or are you just, as I said, collecting knowledge, scholastic information and all the other kind of secondary things for which you could go for 10-15 hours of quote-unquote study and not get a step closer to the actual meaning of those phenomena that are visible here and now while you're doing it?
[SPEAKER_00]: I suppose also, you know, okay, I'm bored, kind of restless or whatever, so I'm going to do something, so that I'm reading suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, you're always, you're not acting out, you're not going for sensual things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you are still aware of that mind being bored.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm not really cultivating craving there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just like, whatever is covering up that state of mind, that's the wrong thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever is leaving it seen, visible, no matter even if it's bored or angry, lustful, as long as that's not covered up.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, yeah, that's the motivation.
[SPEAKER_02]: That, like, if you uncover your motivation, then things are clear.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't matter what state of mind it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's not like, oh, I shouldn't be reading the suttas now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's... everything is a distraction.
[SPEAKER_02]: I must just stay with this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you might factually still need to read the suttas.
[SPEAKER_02]: You need the right reminders, the right context, the new angles to make you pierce through these obtuse kind of phenomena and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, even if you do it out of desire, even if you do it out of restlessness, yeah, it can go only so far.
[SPEAKER_02]: The suttas can't point you back into centrality as other aspects of entertainment or careless, pointless work can.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, yes, even that, fundamentally, the time will come when you recognize, okay, but even this now needs to be abandoned.
[SPEAKER_02]: But don't start abandoning that before the major things are still not even trained in.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I must stop reading the suttas because everything is a desire.
[SPEAKER_02]: And don't read the suttas, remain equally trapped by the desire, manage to hold the floodgates for a while, but without a deeper understanding and insight and knowledge, you will go back to those things like you did before.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, again, purification of the gold.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't be... you're not removing microscopic impurities while it's still, like, indistinguishable from mud.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if the coarse entertainment is not followed, you might catch yourself doing this project or that project.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, again, if there is self-awareness, you will put a lid on it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're like, okay, let's... let's not go too far.
[SPEAKER_02]: Let's not... And, certainly, you won't feel justified in it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think that's also the major aspect of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: When people think, okay, I'm not breaking the principle of entertainment.
[SPEAKER_02]: Therefore, any project in the monastery or dhamma-related is justifiable in and of itself, and I don't have to think about it, and I can just commit to it and do it, and sort of coast off it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's like... no, that's... it's as ignorant as the stuff you were doing before.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you will be doing that to some degree, you'll be catching yourself in doing it, but then, if you're not justifying it, that's already containing it, that's already putting on, that's already limiting it, how far your distraction within keeping the entertainment precepts can go.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yes, you catch yourself reading the suttas, one day, two days, five days, doesn't matter, but as I said, there is always the broader recognition of
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, yeah, you know, the pressure of boredom or distraction was too strong.
[SPEAKER_02]: I couldn't say no.
[SPEAKER_02]: I didn't go to entertainment.
[SPEAKER_02]: I did something else.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm not justifying it.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm not hiding responsibility.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm keeping an eye on my mind while I'm doing it, so that it becomes even more familiar, so that next time, like, I don't have to do it for those reasons, or gradually.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how you sort of, like, like, like, as I said, gradually contain the animal more and more and more.
[SPEAKER_02]: Through recognition how far you need to go, but through simultaneously knowing that, well, you don't start at the end.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, oh, this is how far I need to go in terms of containing the animal, but I can't start there.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mustn't forget that and start where I need to start, which is the coarse entertainment, absolutely pointless projects that just...
[SPEAKER_02]: You kind of take over your mind with inspiration and everything else, and you don't think about anything else, because you have stuff to do.
[SPEAKER_02]: You minimize that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, if it's your sutta study, reading the suttas, asking questions, you could say, oh, I'm doing that because I'm restless, fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Wait until that becomes the most coarse form of obstacle, and then, okay, now I'll say no to that.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the meantime, keep an eye on it, do not ignore it, certainly don't absolve yourself from it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But don't think like, oh, I'll just stop that, while all the other things are floating around.
[SPEAKER_02]: Unchecked.